first of all I have some friends here
who are visiting from New
Jersey and uh I'd like to introduce uh
sjma Sandy Maria can you guys stand up
dudy would
you
what Ste
[Music]
[Applause]
stean
and zand who's
invisible okay I I want to tell you a
story about them okay you
ready okay first picture you
guys so the day I graduated from
Princeton I went to this place uh I was
22 or something like that and uh this is
called Rashi gimping it's a Mongolian
comic
Mongolian temple in New
Jersey near New York it's about 1 hour
from New York and the way they got to
the United States was a long story 700
years
ago uh they took over
Europe and during World War II D they uh
escaped to a big part uh big about a
thousand people escaped to the United
States and uh they built four temples
like this in New Jersey and uh my
teacher was appointed uh the Abbot of
this Temple okay and uh that's how I met
him he came to speak at Princeton I
heard him speak at Princeton and then I
asked him if I could go stay in this
Temple
and he said okay
but uh nobody in that community at that
time spoke uh you know they weren't used
to an American boy coming into a
Mongolian town and there was like a
thousand or 2,000 Mongolian people and
there's one American Boy and it was hard
it was very very hard and luckily I
could speak Russian and some of them
speak Russian and um it was hard it was
really hard and I was in the wrong place
you know and there was one uh
man who uh was the treasurer of the
temple and he he came to me like the
first day and he said what are you doing
in this town you know and I'm like I
just want to study with it with the
Llama you know can I
stay and then my llama was there he said
yeah you can stay my teacher
said uh but you have to live in the
garage so there was a old garage uh with
the old man there and he said you have
to live in the garage I don't have a
place for you you have to live in the
garage and uh it was a really hard place
and um so I moved into the garage cement
floor sleep on the floor and
one uh Mongolian man came to me very
beautiful man here's his
picture next
picture uh his name is hongor
soo and his wife is here Sandy
sjma
[Applause]
and and he said don't worry I'll take
care of you you can stay I'll take care
of you you know and uh he protected me
for 25 years
you know and he let me stay there and he
gave me a place to sleep and uh he took
care of me and he's this beautiful um
happy person and his son Buie is
here and hungar passed away about three
weeks ago
two yeah August 25th and um so today
we'd like to dedicate uh the fire
offering to him I learned to do fire
offering because of these guys and
everything I learned for 25 years is
because of these guys so uh you have to
thank them
again uh here's a early picture of
hunger and his
wife yeah she's
pretty pretty
foxy and uh that's when I met them it
was 50 years ago and uh we went for
lunch like that that's at your house I
think right yeah
okay uh next
picture uh these are some of their
children and and nieces right and
Maria yeah Maria's child is there and
uh
1977 79 I
forget but we got uh permission to
invite the dama to come to our Temple
and after many many years of waiting and
uh this is the day hongor is in the
background and uh
and those are are the children those
children are now 50 something
yeah and
uh I had a a children's class in uh for
15 years and and they were in my
class okay
next uh this is my teacher when he first
got there and he was quite young at
uh he he started next
picture he started to have
classes
and
[Applause]
and and uh that's the Mongolian Temple
and these guys built it St jman and her
husband built it uh Maran her husband
built it and um they let us have classes
there for free we didn't have to pay and
they allowed us to use the tempo for we
said it's just going to be for a few
weeks uh and it was 25 years we had
classes there uh like every day for four
or five hours for 25 years
and and the group got bigger and bigger
and it got to be thousands of people
they
still very kind and they say okay just
mess up the Temple we'll clean it
up and uh they allowed us to have
classes for 25 years and that's why I
can teach you it's because
of
uh next Picture This Is Me learning to
debate in 1979 the newspaper came and
took a
photo and we had a we got a grant from
the
uh from the national what's it called
Institute for the
Humanities and we had a children's
debating
Grant uh and a children's oral history
Mongolia oral history and it
was chosen the project of the Year by
any and
uh they called me zand was in charge of
it she was how old she was 12 years old
or
something and we did a book we did a
book of debating and we did a book of
The Wheel of Life and uh it was selected
the the project of the year for the
country the whole
country and the government uh called me
and said the the director should come
down to Washington
DC and we'll give them a medal or
something and
uh so uh I said well who's G
to who's going to be with her on the
airplane and they said why and I said
she's 12 years old and they're like no
no she can't come and they can they
didn't know she's 12 years old and she
did a whole book about debating and uh
oral history of the Mongolian Buddhism
and uh so it was the grant it was the
best Grant of the year and the kids the
kids group did that yeah next
picture this is um hungar fixing his
son's tie at the damus visit and he had
that's Buie I
think
[Applause]
uh and Buie is an artist and when we had
a bad blog print of The Wheel of Life
painting so we took it over to his house
his mom's house and we asked him if he
could uh fix the carving and here it
is
I think you were 12 or something like
that yeah I think I was he was 12 and uh
we had special genius kids group and uh
they they all did stuff like this so he
he fixed that painting uh and we put it
on the Wheel of Life okay I've been uh
studying that so that
was that was about 50 years ago 45 years
ago and I've been studying The Wheel of
Life still since then and next picture
we just finished this
book uh so this is by
Sugi and uh so gang just finished this
book it took seven years of hard work
and uh it's uh coming out of the work
that we did 45 years ago and I taught
you the first two links
today uh and that's why I can teach you
the first two links is because they they
let me stay in their town and and learn
everything and and it was hard for them
they had a lot of
criticism uh there was a lot of people
who said this white boy should get
kicked out and and they protected me
thank you for
[Applause]
that
uh we have a very cool guy called John
Dutchman here he's been volunteering
here for I don't know almost 10 years or
something and he works really really
hard really
quietly uh very hard work and uh he's
been a very steady worker here for many
years
and one of his jobs used to be to take
all the garbage to the dump and he saw
all this wood extra wood and he said why
should we waste the wood we should make
some benches uh and and then he goes all
over this is a thousand acres he hikes
all over he carries the wood with him
when he sees a nice tree he builds a
bench and he puts it there secretly and
he doesn't tell anybody so if you hike
around and you see these benches uh
that's John Dutchman uh and so I I had
an idea to build a bench in honor of
hungar and a nice
uh
shelter and a bench over looking the
beautiful part of the land and we'll
dedicate it to hongor and we'll have a
plaque for
hongor and uh so I asked John to take me
I said pick a good spot John
because he knows this land like nobody
knows this land so uh here's a this is
where I saw this lady running
there we went up on a mountain if you
guys have time I'll take you up there
it's a little difficult to get
up I was puffing and huffing but uh we'd
like to put a special bench like a stone
bench John's gonna design it
and a shelter over it to give the shade
and John chose a spot where there's a
big tree and there's a good uh place
where you can
spy on all the Retreats which is so I
might go there
sometimes make
sure you guys ready there's a small it's
like a one minute video
here with
down I
[Music]
hope
no
[Music]
it's
coming if you guys want to go to the
last slide and then work on the video
you want to do
that
oh okay then come back to the video okay
all right uh this is a book uh that we
did
uh the uh the Mongolian temple in New
Jersey
has a lot of very very rare
paintings and they have the only
complete copy of the congur in the
United
States uh and
um there's a story Shard
mg who was a Dr Monk which is mg means
Dr Monk in
Mongol and when they left their Homeland
in Europe there was a Mongolian country
there called kikia
and when they left during the war
everyone started to pack their furniture
on the
wagon and shanj got up and said we don't
need furniture we need our
culture and he threw all the furniture
off the wagon and they put all the
religious statues all the religious
paintings and on a wagon with horses
they took them out and they
survived and they came to New
Jersey and uh we did a book of those
paintings uh and there's set of 15 rare
paintings and there's about
200 tiny tiny tiny inscriptions of the
life of Jetson Kaa so uh it took 15
years to to photograph all the paintings
you guys don't know the story but I can
tell you
now I asked my teacher can I take the
paintings down and can I photograph them
and he said
no and uh so one day when he went to the
grocery store in
linin uh I took them all
down and uh I photographed all of them
and then I put them all up and just I
putting up the last one his car came
back and
[Music]
uh and then uh when we check the film
they're all no good you you can't see
anything only the glass
reflection and so the next time he went
on a
trip uh I had like five
hours and we we got them all down we
took them out of the
frames and we photographed them one by
one and we put them back in the frames
nail the frames together put them back
up and then he came home and uh that's
all these that's all these
paintings and uh I told the temple guys
and there's a history of the temple
here uh there's the whole history of the
temple in New
Jersey uh and
uh I I told them uh I'll make a book and
you guys allow me to use all the temple
paintings we'll make 1,000
copies uh we'll sell it for $100
each and we'll donate 100% of the money
to the temple and they said okay and uh
took me a long time to sell the books
Jenny Wong helped me a lot we had a book
selling party and
Singapore
and and uh we just sold out we finished
selling and they took the money and they
renovated the temple and they just put
all the they just changed all the
windows in the temple so thank you for
that uh people asked me can I buy the
book I said no it's finished you know so
we made a
paperback uh which is much
cheaper and here's the paperback uh and
there's the QR code if you want to buy
it you can buy the paperback I think
there's also an ebook it's an ebook also
so uh and we have
paintings uh modern some modern
paintings were done uh by an Nancy
Nancy
n no New York Nancy Nancy Karen's son or
Karen he painted this uh paintings the
painting on the
left is a
Dream by its some ca's
mother and uh she didn't know she was
pregnant with SOA and uh she had a dream
that she was in a field with 500 other
women
and my juy was going from woman to woman
with vaji aini and say is it this one
and she go no they said is it this one
they said no and then they got to sona's
mother and my asked jini is this is this
her and he said yep that's the right one
so then she got
pregnant and she had uh Jets on Kaa okay
so if you want to get this uh book
uh we continue to support the temple and
for
me uh we should help that Temple for the
rest of our life okay it's a small
Temple but uh 25 years of
classes uh no charge my teacher would
not take money and um they didn't take
money from us for 25 years and we had
classes there and we spilled stuff on
the floor
and made a mess
and everything I learned to do fire
offering there so uh tonight the fire
offering will be for
hunger uh before that uh bie is a rock
star I don't know why my student should
grow up as a rock
star but he's gonna play some music for
us before the fire offing to celebrate
his father
and before that we're going to have a
wedding uh these two
[Applause]
guys so that starts at what time you
guys
5:30 5:30 wedding 5:31
dancing and then uh 6:30 uh fire
offering dress warm I I guess it's a
little chilly today so dress warm the
fire offing will be right outside there
the rock and roll will be right here
okay he said maybe he let me help
Stephen with the base I don't know but
uh we'll negotiate
that you the Grateful Dead would have
two drummers and maybe two bass players
I don't know uh but uh anyway uh we'll
celebrate hur's life if
if if hongor didn't if hongor wasn't
there I wouldn't be here and and his
father their their husband and
father uh he he helped me to survive for
25 years otherwi I won't be here
[Music]
[Applause]
okay
Maria was also the best student of my
teacher among no in the community uh she
was the best Mongolian student of my
teacher so if you have any toban
questions ask
her and she has some beautiful children
also oh don't embarrass
me just might I just want to add that
the 15 um tonas they're from
Lassa yeah they're from Lassa they're
from laa and his whole owners his family
owned them at one point they were
brought out on horse on Horseback during
the fighting during the fighting yeah uh
okay I'll show you the video of where
we're going to put the hongor memorial
bench and shelter and people can go
there and enjoy the land and relax it's
it's a 30 second video
sorry might bug
24 in 24 we don't have very
often you know if we have this three
month
retreaters so that's where we build a
plat we'll build a a shade and a bench
and we already have a
sponsor called gesla and his wife
and and uh we're gonna build a place
that were're people can relax and look
at the
land and I can spy to see if people are
doing their Retreat
okay yeah and if you guys have time uh
we can drive up there but it's it's
pretty high place but it's a beautiful
place
yeah so that'll be the hongor Sul
Memorial Shelter okay all right and
please enjoy your time here uh please
make sure they
overeat and uh and take good care of
them okay they took care of me for 25
years
okay all right let's go we'll go back to
class and we'll do the other thing okay
guys all right we'll go back to
[Music]
class let's see
here I was thinking to start at
5.41 which is a sick
lady okay I keep jumping around and I'm
sorry that's gisha
add Tim we go till nine right
okay okay uh the there's eight medicine
Buddhas uh which is seven medicine
Buddha gang plus their Road
manager which is Lord Buddha
shakuni and
uh the first Buddha is called good name
okay and good name made eight famous
prayers we're going to cover the most
important ones and so the first P prayer
of the first medicine Buddha is for sick
people okay and it's a prayer here's the
prayer
5.42
yeah when never those of us here or
those like us any living being at all
are stricken by blindness or deafness or
Insanity or skin diseases or some
terrible illness may all their senses be
is stored and all their pain and
sickness come to stum in all the days to
come until we come to our final
Enlightenment okay that's the first
prayer of the first Buddha
uh you guys spent some time we
translated the two sutras of medicine bu
and it was a lot of work it took about
five years or something and we published
it and it's
done and you can read those sutras and
you can
do a retreat with those sutras
okay uh or you can use the fifth dius
sna which now you have the first two
parts of the three parts and there's a
very
very important uh emphasis in the fifth
Dilma okay and it's different from the
Sutra okay Sutra
says may sick people people
uh may may sick people get cured okay
that's the first prayer in the SRA okay
here's the first prayer in the fifth
dilemma may we get
cured okay and it's from the first
person it's from me you know and you're
praying that that I may be cured also so
really there's a new
emphasis in the in this s and it's
is I'm also sick I also get sick I'm
also going to die and may please help us
okay so the prayer in the
Sutra is largely for other people and
the prayer in the sadna includes
yourself okay and it's a big big
difference when you're doing
Retreat uh you're not just saying to the
eight medicine buddh please take care of
other people you're saying please take
care of everybody including me okay so
sometimes Buddhist people get too
focused on taking care of all living
beings and my teacher used to say uh
don't forget you is one of all living
beings okay you is one of all living
beings okay so when you're praying for
all living beings it's okay to
include yourself because you're are also
suffering and you are one of those
living beings
you shouldn't leave yourself out when
you take care of people and that applies
to Tracy's question you know it's a very
very Buddhist
practice to take care of your own self
also you you can't take care of other
people and ignore yourself shoing you
have to take care of your own heal you
have to take care that you sleep enough
you know to if you hurt your yourself to
help other people you are making
medicine Buddha
unhappy okay uh you are one of the
people that you're supposed to take care
of okay so don't forget that my teaching
used to say uh all living beings
including
you he say all all includes you okay so
that's a big difference in the fif okay
he wants you to be aware that you you
have a commitment to take care of
yourself also okay otherwise you can't
take care of other people all right cool
all right next
one uh then the medicine budha says
there by the way there is no
cure okay you you you
should you should
pray that every living being gets cured
of old age and sickness but by the way
there's no
cure okay that this is one of those
strange medicine
Buddha announcements you know you have
to make sure everyone gets cured and
there is no cure okay so let's talk
about that all
[Music]
right and we're going to go to
uh back to the Gan and next next slide
you guys
um this is one of the most famous
quotations from wisdom okay if I taught
you nara's most
important book of poems if I taught you
carefully it would take about 10 years
and we couldn't do anything else okay uh
so I took the most important uh verses I
I'm giving you the highlights like the
football highlights okay of wisdom okay
and this has to be one of the top five
verses okay of all of that book written
2,000 years ago uh this is this is one
of the most famous verses if you want to
memorize some
Nagina memorize this one okay this is
very very famous
okay
okay uh wisdom the book is in poetry
which makes it beautiful because it's in
poetry we're using it for
the parenting course how to be a good
parent okay you
guys s JMA I'm teaching a parenting
course I've never been a parent and uh
so I'm an expert and uh but but we're
basing it on this poetry this is the
Poetry that we're basing it on okay and
uh the original poetry is also a debate
the original poetry is also a debate
it's an argument between ngoga and other
people other people attack
ngog and they they say if things are
empty then I I don't see how it's going
to work I don't see how it's going to
work you know this is not neog this
verse which I just told you to memorize
is not Nar it's his opponent it's a very
very
famous criticism of ngar okay his
opponent
says uh is everything empty according to
you narian or what narian say yeah of
course I I told you like over and over
everything's empty okay okay so it's
empty nothing starts and Nothing Stops
like
cancer doesn't start and you can't stop
cancer right if nothing exists it can't
start and it can't stop right who said
that the other guy the other guy if
everything is emptiness how do you say
emptiness in in kic I don't
know a aen yeah in
uh in tibetan Tom in Sanskrit sh
okay in chinesee
K in
Russian in Spanish
vak okay I don't know what else in
German
[Applause]
lyp okay uh I teach all over the world I
have to know that's the only word I know
okay uh if everything's empty then
nothing nothing starts and Nothing Stops
okay and according to you the first
teaching of the Buddha is
cancelled who's who's
talking his his opponent yeah his
opponent oh oh everything's empty right
the G yes so nothing starts right right
and Nothing Stops right right so cancel
the four truths cancel the first
teaching on Lord Buddha okay cancel what
the first thing that Lord Buddha ever
said you know the four AR TRS Teddy gave
them last time but he's not here which
means suang has to do it
loudly so the first one is it's a
Singapore
accent s por the first one is life is
suffering and then
life is suffering okay and then there's
a cause of suffering that has a cause
and then there's a way to stop it
no we can stop the cause of the
suffering then there's a path to stop
and there's a way okay uh we we live in
pain it has a cause you can stop it and
there's a path to stop it but since
narina everything's empty then nothing
starts
in the first no two Noble ARA truth and
Nothing Stops in the second two ARA
truths I guess we can cancel
Buddhism okay who's
talking the other guy very very famous
okay I'll give
[Applause]
$1,000 and I hate it when people answer
before
before I ask a
question Rob's getting nervous we got we
got a thousand it's GNA clean me
out okay now I don't offer a thousand
unless it's really important okay and so
listen carefully and I really will give
you a
thousands uh if you can answer the
question okay and these these questions
go down in history the guy who's coming
tomorrow for his translation class got
3,000 out of me one
day for a question I never thought he
could
answer so here's the here's the question
someone attacks Naga okay if
everything's as empty as you say then
nothing starts and nothing stops for
example in the context of medicine
Buddha cancer high blood pressure
anything else it doesn't start according
to you cuz it's empty and you can't stop
it either so I guess medicine Buddha are
all going to retire right cuz they got
nothing to do according to you narina
the four truths don't exist at all
now look at look at that verse okay and
I'll I'll tell you something and that's
the Thousand bet Stanley woke up
completely
uh there comes a another verse later in
the chapter and it's an answer to this
verse there comes another verse later in
the chapter we'll get to it and it's an
answer to this
verse uh if you can tell
me that later verse I'll give you $1
thousand dollar by the way you want a
clue
yes I don't know if I should tell
you you don't need to see the other
verse to tell me what it
is okay raise your hand she's choosing
not
me okay and if you win the $1,000 you're
taking us all out to dinner
no because they empty they
exist here's the verse here's the here's
the here's what you have to do to win
the money there's a verse that comes
later
which attacks this verse without seeing
that verse you can tell me what it is
and you win
$1,000 my guess is because they empty
they
exist give me the whole verse come on
work for your
money I'll give you a clue you want
another
clue change one word
come down she's gonna do it and she's
taking me to
dinner because they empty from their
nature they exist now
listen then the the verse that comes
later is Nina's answer and he just
changes one word and that's his
answer share the money with her
please okay uh it is the same words
without cannot according to you uh the
four higher
truths can
exist anybody
else and you guys you guys look like the
kids in
my in my elementary school when the
teacher said you have to go to the
bathroom and
everybody
uh
so all the N starts from their own
side no I just changed one word come
on because they are empty the for truth
can
exist I think Chloe wanted to try what
no you want just okay I'll make it more
and more easy
add one goddamn
word and it's his
answer add one word and it's his answer
you keep the rest of the verse the
same it's so easy
I never mind I'm not answering Tim you
choose okay you're the boss um Julia in
the front
who you the front in in the yellow how
thinky if all of these are empty then
nothing starts and nothing stop
therefore according to you then the four
higher truths
exist you're making it too hard Jose
from
Peru
okay if all this if all these are
empty then everything starts and
everything stops therefore for
no this money is so hard to give
away and listen listen I'm going to
repeat I'm going to repeat just add one
word and you get
$1,000
nothing but you have to read the whole
verse wi you're gonna try wi loud oh she
yes K you have to translate you have
to um if all of these are empty then
nothing and too late too
late you in you
in Ena Ena say that again who's who's
going to translate for
you
no somebody else uh I'll say how say if
St
if could
May then
may Tina got it but it's kind of late
it's kind
[Music]
of I Tim up to you um give it back to
enaa right behind you to your left this
is the hardest money I ever
G all of this are not empty
[Music]
yay
[Applause]
by the way if you share the money with
Tim it's
[Applause]
corruption n uh uh uh uh cannot cannot
that would be corruption yeah okay good
right then so the guy complained to Naga
hey if all this stuff is empty then
nothing stops and then nothing starts so
why the hell Buddha taught the four
truths because the whole the four truths
the first two are about how things start
how trouble starts and the second two
are about how to stop it so according to
you there's no
Buddhism and the g answer is if they're
not empty you're
right got it which means if they're not
coming from
you then there's no Buddhism okay if
things are not coming from you then
there's no Buddhism I agree he said if
things are coming from you there's no
Buddhism and the g said no if things are
not coming from you there's no buddham
you can't cure cancer unless it comes
from
you you cannot cure
cancer unless it comes from you
got it because it comes from you you
have a chance and by the way I grew up
Christian and my wife is The Devout
Christian and I loved the Christian
church that tree was in the Christian
church I that's where I met her and uh
but this is a big big difference right
this is a big big difference you know
the world does not come if the world
does not come from you you will always
suffer because there's no reason why it
should change you see what I mean
got it
okay it's so hard to give you guys
money
uh I I I you can give me money much
easier
uh okay let's go to the then I didn't I
don't want to go through good names
prayers one by one I want to take the
the most serious the Highlight prayers
okay and so here's the next one uh next
picture you guys at Tim at 15 till we'll
have this party
okay uh this is the Gaza Strip uh the
morning I wrote the class okay this is
uh stop this is
uh I don't know how many people died
that morning 500 people died 500 people
in a hospital died down this is a
hospital that blew up in the in uh
Israel in Palestine okay this is the in
this explosion 500
people 500 wounded people died okay uh
so let's go to the next prayer okay
let's go to the next
PR there are those of us what's
significant
here yeah he says us you know we we and
the other people are suffer suffering
from poverty we don't have food we don't
have clean water we don't have clothing
we don't have money crops places to
stay nothing to offer either no incense
no flowers in a for a Buddhist this is a
disaster I don't have enough money to
buy offerings you know and that's what's
the situation of those people right now
they can't get water they can't get fuel
they can't get food okay right now okay
and
when you see it I think when you see it
on the news we
should do our Retreat better you see
what I mean like what can I do about a
gesla I'm not there I don't have
millions of dollars I can't take care of
them but you can you can do your
practice you can do your sna okay so do
your
sna for them okay do your son who's
right who's wrong it it never mattered
the in history it never mattered was it
the Germans was it the Mongolians was it
the Americans was it the British was it
the Russians was it the ukrainians was
it the Palestinians was it the Jews it
doesn't matter that what matters is can
we stop it okay I I don't care who
started it that's that's a useless game
sansar is a circle with no beginning
okay sansara is a circle with no
beginning who started it nobody
if you go there you're going to spend
your whole life looking for who started
it okay all right uh so it's happening
now what can we do here's the this is
the fourth prayer of good name okay we
went from prayer number one which was
for sick people and now we're going to
prayer number four for people with
nothing to eat and nothing to nothing to
take care of
themselves
uh next
picture
yeah this is like helping a homeless
person and um I'll tell you something
interesting
uh that book that we quoted this morning
by
Dy where he said like I don't care if
nobody wants this book I'm GNA write it
anyway okay that's how I feel in the
translator uh you know
uh he said stop that
uh he said Buddha has achieved both of
the goals okay Buddha has achieved both
of the goals it's called rangun punok
and shend P say
rangun shinden sh
pun Buddha has finished taking care of
other people and Buddha has finished
taking care of Buddha very famous this
is kind of the definition of ab Buddha
Buddha has finished taking care of other
people and Buddha has finished taking
care of
himself and then there's a famous famous
objection what do you think it is for
zero
dollars if if Buddha took care of
everybody else why are people getting
blown up in a hospital yesterday why 500
people many of them children why would
they they were already wounded then they
were killed you know they they were
wounded and they were operating on them
with no uh anesthesia because there's no
no
anesthesia and then they bombed the
whole hospital they blew up the whole
thing anyway you know so how can you
claim that Buddha took care of himself
and everybody else also it's a very
famous objection to to dharm
maties by the way ACI course number two
Refuge you know you're going to uh
Refuge to a person who has the two
Perfection they took care of everything
and then you say how can you say they
took care of everything if yesterday 500
kids got blown up you know how can you
say that you know and they said he did
he did take care of everything he took
care everything for himself and he took
care of everything for other people he
finished he's finished Buddha's finished
Buddha took care of himself and BR took
care of other
people because there's nothing more to
do okay there's nothing more to do teach
them that these things are coming from
yourself and you and and there's nothing
more you can do for somebody you cannot
take another person's Karma you cannot
take another person's Karma Buddha
cannot take another person's Karma once
Buddha taught you that your world is
coming from you that's all Buddha can do
for you there's nothing else Buddha now
you have to take care of yourself you
have to finish your seeds Okay a Buddha
cannot take you have millions of seeds
in
your Storehouse Consciousness right
Buddha cannot change one Buddha cannot
change one Buddha if if he could he
would take all your seeds but he cannot
okay and that's a big question about God
or Christianity if God made everything
why PE God make people with cancer you
know and Buddha would say God cannot
take away your cancer you have to take
away your cancer okay but God taught you
how so God took care of you I'm sorry
Buddha took care of you okay or maybe
God also okay if they taught you they
took care of you because they cannot
take they cannot take away your seeds
it's not possible okay if it was
possible no one would have
cancer if if it's possible for another
person to take away your bad seeds no
one would have cancer or else that
person has no
compassion okay if it's possible for
another person to take away your bad
seeds and people still get cancer either
they could not do it or they have no
love for people at all and they don't
mind to watch a hospital blow up with
500 kids in it you know got it okay all
right
all right
uh I'm going to shift now uh I'm going
to do it Tim
and we'll come back to it okay um I have
a presentation for you guys where is
that it's a new
plan
okay my wife when I say new plans she
like goes to the bathroom or
something enough plans
enough
projects when I start to say I got an
idea she's like
[Laughter]
no it's like you don't have
time anyway my new idea me and Tim we
had uh total it was about 11 hours of
fundraising to work yesterday and uh on
my day off and uh we call it 3033 plan
okay you guys 30 promise I don't know
it's promise I said
plan uh 30 30 30 plan okay so here's the
idea okay uh I I started ACI 30 years
ago this year is the 30th
anniversary of uh of ACI okay I'll show
you a little bit about what we have done
in the last 30 years okay what you know
we started ACI 30 years ago with five
people around a kitchen
table in Hell's Kitchen and if you don't
know what Hell's Kitchen is You' never
been there okay and this is a the part
of New York around the Port Authority
Bus Terminal south of the
terminal which is extremely dangerous
and uh this is where we did our first
classes okay this is where we had the
first classes on they there were five
people in the room Annie pmer was
there and uh I remember we went out to
buy Refreshments for the uh students and
there's a a guy walking down the street
with a without any clothes on it with a
pistol like this this is Hell's Kitchen
you know and AE P was like what's that
and and I'm like get across the street
you know and this is Hell's Kitchen why
were we there because it's cheap
uh we couldn't afford uh a place to hold
the classes we didn't have a commic
community to give us a temple for 25
years we had to pay rent and that was
really hard and it was it was very very
difficult uh so anyway uh here's what we
did there next
line no is it how about yeah uh I would
say you know Buddha gave three major
parts of his life there's three major
parts of the Buddhist life they call
turning of the wheel the Buddha had the
Buddhist teaching
career had three major parts okay we
call the three turning of the wheel uh
the first turning for us for all of us
was called the 18 Foundation courses of
ACI okay uh it took seven years in New
York City I was working more than
full-time
and we did classes four nights a week I
think and uh it was really hard uh
really really hard and uh so we finished
uh 18 courses and it's
4,657 pages of translation it's the most
important parts of the gashi course okay
if you finish the 18 Foundation courses
you you know all the material of the
gishi course I had a famous dinner
with Juan hasso
and or vas with gashi lar brought two of
his gishi candidates senior gishi
candidates Hara I'm not a senior I'm a
baby gishi I'm a third level gishi these
are first level gishi two of them and
they had a debate and Hassle and Orit
beat the two
gishes and and I was
like
yeah yeah it was kind of funny um but uh
those Foundation courses are good stuff
and they're I almost said something else
right they're good stuff okay and it
took seven hard years uh to translate
them okay then I told the students who
survives the first 18
courses uh I'll teach you Tantra Diamond
way and we'll have a special course for
Diamond way next
slide yeah that took seven
years uh it happened here at diamond
mountain and uh it's it's 7,000 so
together it's 12,000 pages of
translation and it was hard it was
really really
hard and uh so the first 18 courses
those are uh the gashi course it's and
if
you study them well you can beat a
gishi okay I think I saw
it okay then the second uh the second
cour is the diamond
way uh it's 18 courses about the secret
teachings and the nature of the secret
teachings is that were secret so they
weren't very well organized uh somebody
taught three people here somebody taught
two people there and no one ever put
them all together uh it never happened
in history that all the different t uh
teachings were put together into a
course and that's that's the ACI course
that's the first time in history and I I
say without I'm not shy to say it's the
best Ted course
in in the last 2,000 years it's amazing
and it's accurate and it's it's it's
correct and it works okay so uh we
finished that it took seven hard years
we call Blood Sweat and Tears right and
we had a lot of problems when you do
something important you get a lot of
problems okay if you're trying to keep
your Temple alive in New
Jersey in it if it's the only Temple in
a thousand miles you're going to get
problems cuz the demons don't like it
okay they don't like it they will when
you stick your head up they come to to
hit you you know when you build a
temple uh or you start a tter course
seven-year course you're going to
someone's going to come and try to you
know this is the nature okay so we
finished it took seven years okay
then
uh we started L
Rim okay and uh I promise to finish the
long
Rim uh it will take 21 years to finish
the L room okay it will take 21 years we
finished 14
years okay we're
done this year is 14th year start
okay which means I have seven years to
go I will be
77 hopefully my mind will hold out I
don't worry about my niece I can teach
in a chair but uh I got to hope the Mind
holds out okay so uh I need to do uh
seven more years okay and to for me to
finish the alarm I I need seven more
years and my intention
is to uh do a 100
meditations so videos on video the I I
think the time of books is passing and
I'm sad to see them go I love them very
much but we don't need paper anymore I I
have on here three million pages of
Buddhist books I I have all my books I
don't know what to do with them I gave
them to John Brady to keep in his
office uh I have hundreds of Tibetan
books I don't need them I haven't used
them for 25 years finally I just came to
jum here you guys keep them you know
there's 3 million Pages here uh there's
200 there's 300,000 books cataloged here
you know so uh it's it's
enough uh so I need we have books we
have the 18 courses we have 12,000 pages
of courses what we don't have is a
meditation series a series of
meditations and I'm talking a hundred
meditations people ask me oh you taught
me T yeah uh you taught me DJ yeah is
that it is that all there is no I mean
in the monastery you do a 100
meditations you master a 100 meditations
during the gesi course you master a
hundred different
meditations and I would like to uh
record them and I would like to make
videos I think the next big step Arena
this morning where are you she gave me
my what's it called insta account
Instagram
Instagram I didn't know she's doing it
she says Gua you're a star you got half
a million hits I'm like did someone hit
me and then she's like no no and uh
I think the next I think if I'm G to
finish my job I got to make videos like
a 100 videos and I'd like to do a 100
videos of uh to for the whole L room so
it'll take 21
years to teach you the L Rim but I would
like to uh distill it to 100 videos I'd
like to make a 100
meditations that and make a 100 videos
that we can do I have seven years left
we we won't finish for seven years okay
we have seven more years to
go here's the here's the here's what I'm
asking for today okay um it's been 30
years
uh since we started ACI uh
in in in seven years uh that'll be 30
years of of those courses okay uh I'm
sorry 2030
I will finish the alarm room okay so
there's 30 and 30 okay was it in 2030 I
will finish the third turning of the
wheel uh and it's been 30 years since I
founded ACI okay so 30 and 30 okay uh
ACI has a we had a board meeting
yesterday day before and and Tim was
like pulling out his hair you know like
how do I pay for all is and I said we
have 20
organizations in the worldview group we
organizations and you were given the
most impossible job and he said what and
I said you have to teach thousands and
thousands of people in 12 languages
around the world for
free and he's like what and I'm like
that's the problem with ACI ACI can
never work whoever you choose as
director of ACI is going to pull out
their hair okay and I can tell you you
know I paid for everything for the first
seven years one person helped me a
little bit uh but I paid for everything
I used to print the homeworks at the
temple at 2 o'clock in the morning and
then they were done by 6:00 and I put
them in a backpack and I Carri them to
New York cuz no one wants to pay for
them they want everything free you know
and then I rented a place to teach the
classes in New York and it was expensive
I was in a huge debt when I finished the
tantry course I was $30,000 in debt at
that time it was a lot of money it's
like $100,000 now I I moved to Rimrock
with with the debt I didn't have I had
zero money nothing because I whoever
gets to choose whoever is appointed the
director of ACI is appointed an
impossible job because they they have to
teach people all over the world by the
way there's 200,000 students total in
the world right now all all
worldview and all there's 19 worldview
organizations that charge money there's
one that's not allowed to charge that's
ACI they charge for extra stuff you know
you can sign up $99 and you get you know
Tim will tell your future or
something I don't know but the basic
courses are free so we have a
fundamental problem if I'm going to
continue for seven years either I can do
the hundred meditation videos or I can
fundraise but I don't have goddamn time
to do both I cannot do it I cannot do it
I tried I really try I can't do it okay
you choose the course or the fundraising
but I will die if I have to do both it's
impossible I spent 11 hours yesterday
I'm supposed to prepare the class I
can't do it I just can't do it so we we
have to pay for ACI okay somebody has to
pay for ACI somebody asked me keep
everything free G I said I fly United
Airlines you come with me they came to
the ticket office I said they want the
course for free okay can I have an
airplane ticket for free and they said
get out of
here you we have to pay for some stuff
there's some stuff we have to pay for
okay so we have a new proposal 30 30 30
30 it's 30 years since we found an
ACI I can finish in
2030 if everybody give $1 a
day
okay
okay uh voluntarily okay if you say I
don't want to pay $1 here I want to come
to class for free right in the temple
not only they come for free they spill
stuff on the floor you know I spent two
hours every night after suu to clean the
floor uh me and me and syn made the
floor with Hunger we put the remember we
put the tiles down with a torch and uh
you know not only will they not pay they
will complain and they will spill crap
on the floor and then they'll leave and
somebody has to clean out so anyway uh
if
everybody give
30 dollars a month just sign up it's
like call it super
Netflix you
know like super Netflix
and everyone just sign up okay I'll pay
$1 a month okay then how long Des I'm
going till
2 30 okay I'm going to 2030 so at least
until then after that I don't care it's
up to Tim okay no I care but I think if
you get in the habit to pay $1 a day
then it's not going to hurt you I mean
how
many I'm not even going to ask you I got
Netflix Hulu Disney every time I want a
new movie I have to sign up for the
stupid thing you can cancel in two
months who
cancels I get this bill with I never
heard of this one this my wife says well
that's that movie we wanted to see you
know so it's just you're not going to
miss it okay 30 so that's 30330 right 30
years we've been doing it we're going to
2030 you're going to pay 30 every month
okay and here's the last 30 me and my
friend nor who we have a charity with
SII we have a charity with Rob russer we
have a charity right we will pay the
first
$30,000
today okay we we will give the first
$30,000 today
okay and his heart
it's but we have it we we worked really
hard this month and we
we we collect it from everywhere so
we'll give the first
30,000 if there's other big sponsors who
want to give 30,000 or or 300 or 3,000
I'm not going to
complain okay so if you want to match or
help uh and and I know we're asking for
funds for a lot of projects and I know
that and I'm sorry but I'm not
sorry okay the reason we have 20
projects 20 organizations is because
they're helping different people okay uh
there's 20 organizations because each
one helps a different
population and that's why 20
organizations are asking you for money
and that's why tomorrow I'm going to ask
you for more money for another
organization uh okay but
right now my heart will be at ease for
the next seven years if I don't have to
fundraise if I just know it's taken care
of okay it's not a lot of money but we
need it we need to pay people we need to
pay for the tech we are we are paying
people who don't have other jobs if if
you dedicate your life to ACI and you're
you're you're like a tech person for ACI
full-time then it's cruel to ask those
people to do that then how are they
supposed to feed their kids or how they
supposed to take care of their family
you know it's we used to be all
volunteer but it's just not possible if
you're working eight hours a day 10
hours a day you got to give people
something so that 30 the $30 a month
will hopefully take care of that okay
and we're we're trying to find a
thousand people to give 30 and then and
then we'll be okay
and then I can focus on on the third
turning of the wheel it takes me seven
give me seven more years with no
fundra and uh that's my
Nirvana you know and let me focus on on
the godd dam course you know and I mean
I'll always do it if I have to fundraise
I will and I'm I'm good at it because my
teacher taught me to
fundraise and um and I'll do it I'm
happy to do it and I'm I won't complain
I know I complain BR but I'm happy to do
it I'll do it if I have to do it I'll do
it I'll do both but I can I can do it I
know I can I can do a better job with
the videos 100 videos and and and what
happens you see in in the old days and
then I'll finish okay in the old days
there's two ways to get time two ways to
go to vajana number one become a
gishi GIS are allowed to enter the two
tantry colleges that the ticket to enter
a the only two places to learn T and to
B the ticket is a g degree you cannot
enter those two colleges without G my
teacher entered and became the vice
president of the tattoo College because
he was a high G okay so either you get a
g or
if you finish l r with a qualified
teacher you're allowed to go to
Tundra okay if you finish l r with a
qualified teacher you're allowed to go
to T okay so my idea is if we have the
meditations uh and you master them you
can go to vajana this way this is
traditional this is traditional you have
option sweat through the 18 courses
7,000 pages of work the homeworks are
long
[Music]
okay or Master the 100 meditations of
the L room okay and then you go to V
okay diamond diamond way gesla what does
it mean to master the 100 meditations of
the
L when you can teach them you master it
how else are we going to know you're not
blinking you see I mean how are we going
to judge your knowledge of a meditation
I can't watch you you you know oh look
Tina moved she failed you know I I can't
judge if you mastered a meditation until
I see you teach it see what I mean until
I see you share it I don't know if you
understand it if you can lead the
meditation with your eyes
closed then you mastered the meditation
they are not hard they are not weird you
don't have to memorize 200 things it's a
feeling I want you to see if you have
the feeling of that meditation okay you
passed meditation number 28 now going to
29 okay when you can teach 100
meditations and they're not complicated
and there's not a lot to memorize or
something like that when you can teach
them with heart from your heart you pass
you see what I mean and then then you do
diamond way okay ideally you can do
both
uh but it's also another way to end
traditionally my teacher's
sister who was a quiet old Tibetan lady
we took her on a plane one time in India
and we going to fly her down to the mon
you know and we she lived in darjiling
which is really dor
Ling the land of the
diamond darjiling te is not daring it's
d Ling te it's the land of the diamond
te she was she lived in a tiny and she
had a tiny little Momo shop in d Ling
daring okay she never been on an
airplane before Oh my God you know she's
her Knuckles are like this you know and
the plane took off and I'm watching her
and she's
going she's like shaking she's like 60
years old she was a secret vaj
master she was a secret gashi lar is her
son okay she was a high vaj guini Master
secret and they had a secret ladies bini
group in Dar and they had Stu secretly
for like 30 years okay and nobody knew
and that's perfect Tundra that's real
Tundra oh look this old lady she can't
fly on the airplane this old lady is the
highest vaj yogini master in this part
of India okay and she's secret she looks
like a housewife you know and that's
real uh Diamond wave practice and she
entered through Lum she entered uh Vini
practice through Lam so that's the idea
that's the master plan okay help me out
if you can if you don't I'll do it
anyway but if you do I can have more fun
okay I can have a couple days off to
fundraise for the other
[Applause]
organization okay so uh 3030 here's the
QR
cone
yeah uh when I teach the 100 meditations
I'm going to write a Manga comic book
with 100 meditations in it I call it l
seriously L manga okay so there'll be a
comic
B and 100 videos okay and uh just sign
up okay help help me out okay if you if
you have the capacity to match the 30
the other 30 you're welcome to try
okay all
right
oh
[Applause]
thank
you you do
who
[Music]
1,000
what's
yay
in this lifetime 5000
5,000 Canadian doll I'm so sorry
[Laughter]
Canadian 500 from Peru 5,000 oh my God
[Applause]
W I think I'll drink a slow
coffee I'll give $55 a month for 30
[Applause]
years
okay
[Applause]
I guess I won't go to the bathroom I
just okay okay don't don't worry about
it no
[Music]
[Applause]
pressure okay you guys decide I mean I I
didn't mean to put pressure on you uh
but uh help us out okay okay and uh me
and my me and my work huh oh you sure we
also take B we also take board s1,000
[Music]
y by the way Butchie Steven rock out
uh we'll have instruments here and and
in the whole
day if you want to come it'll it's a
nice place to play it it's a very it's
got a
nice the the room has a nice St so if
you would be
willing uh we can dance if you can
play and uh it's it is after all a
marriage happening today so and we have
lots of musicians
Nick
Jack these are guitar players ERS
drummers keyboard
players okay they can help Okay yeah and
they're
good all right you guys ready you
W5 zillion
dollars
we take
it Timothy first of all thank you all
very thank you thank you so very
much and thank you Gesa for committing
to teach and and having this beautiful
plan for their for their third turning
of your ACI wheel oh money
B